# **Charles Sizer**

charlie@sizer.tech • +1 (630) 452-8359 • 520 Clifton Ave • Sheboygan, WI

#### Summary

Mathematician. Engineer. Analyst. Manager.

*Objective:* Use my start up business experience to obtain a challenging position where I will use my modeling, creative problem-solving, and analytical skills to drive positive business outcomes.

I am a mathematician. I applied my skills to food-

industry R&D and operations where, at a succession of bold start-ups, I honed my business understanding. For nearly fifteen years, I was the go-to when complicated problems needed sophisticated spreadsheets to make them comprehensible. I worked with senior leaders to capture business data and inform company strategies and decisions.

### Experience

#### Boombox Beverage LLC

Skokie, IL

#### Director of Food Safety and Quality

July 2020 - Present

Boombox Beverage is a startup company established, and plant designed, to process and package cold brew coffee. I was selectively hired to bring the plant into compliance with low acid canned food regulations.

Accomplishments

- Created a food safety plan in a chaotic business environment.
- developed KPI dashboard for production tracking.
- Major contributor in key business decisions as part of start-up team leadership
- Hired, trained and, and managed a dedicated Quality Team, a pillar of the organization
- Established Food Safety Program for a startup low acid canned food facility
- Created business policies and the tools to impliment them
- Developed and implemented Food Safety Plan (HARPC) for all products.
- Worked closely with process authority to establish legal thermal processes
- Launched three new products for a national brand
- Driving force behind SQF level 1 certification effort

KD Automation Jackson, WI

## **Systems Integration Manager**

Jackson, vvi July 2019-Feb 2020

Brought onboard to fill gaps in the programming/design team for a large project with on the job training. Worked closely with a cross-disciplinary team to design and build an progressive assembly line.

Major responsibilities

- creation and maintainance of schematics, bills of material, and panel layouts
- assist with electrical panel builds
- program PLCs, HMIs, robots, cameras and other automation devices
- commission machines

#### Dairyvative Technologies

Reedsburg & Sheboygan, WI

## **Director of Technology**

2013 - Oct 2018

Managed the development of a novel dairy product, processing equipment, controls systems, facility, regulatory compliance, and intellectual property for a tech start-up. Worked closely with Sr Management and direct reports to achieve commercialization and R&D goals.

Built and documented Quality Systems to exceed compliance requirements. Managed department budget, hiring and training.

Accomplishments

- Developed new technology for milk preservation with a model-based approach
  - Designed & built commercial-scale prototype based on theory
  - Reduced theory to practice
  - Iteratively improved efficiency, reliability, quality, and safety by leveraging use of historical process data
  - Investigated complex viscosity phenomena of the product by desinging multivariate experiment and using scientific computing tools to analyze the data
- Led a team of 7 through a \$1MM facility build-out
- Commercialized milk preservation process

- Designed custom batching, heat treating, and packaging solution for the process
- Oversaw purchase, fabrication, installation, and commissioning of custom equipment
- Designed and built a standards-complaint food-grade production facility
- Led interactions with Federal and State regulators to determine how the product fit into existing regulatory frameworks
- Developed and deployed an industry leading SCADA system
  - eliminated paper records, reduced compliance burden, minimized down time
  - reduced labor requirements by 75%
  - Developed mechanisms for compliance with digital record keeping regulations (21CFR11)
  - Deployed and maintained full SCADA stack
    - \* Field level: Modbus RTU, 4-20mA loops
    - \* Equipment level: PLC ladder logic, Modbus TCP/RTU, Ethernet/IP, ZPL
    - \* Supervisory level: Custom UI, Jython scripting
    - \* Records & Reporting: SQL, Java, Python/Pandas

## Cambrooke Foods (now a division of Ajinomoto)

AYER, MA

### **Product Development Specialist**

2012-2015

Designed, assembled and commissioned food processing lines for a medical foods company. The lines included a hot-fill line for high-acid beverages and an AlfaLaval low-acid processing line for packaging medical foods on an aseptic Tetra Pak TPA/19. Member of the team that assembled and implemented the HACCP plan. Medical foods are considered the highest risk food category by the FDA since the patients are required to adhere to a strict diet consisting of only medical foods. As such, the facility was the first facility inspected under the Food Safety Modernization Act and passed the inspection with no adverse findings.

#### **Accomplishments**

- On leadership team of \$5MM facility build-out
- Formulated medical food product to meet guidelines for enteric nutrition
- Iterated design of equipment and thermal process to deliver enteric nutrition
- Formulated a protein enhanced rehydration beverage
- Designed process to gently sterilize protein and maximize shelf-life
- Managed small beverage production team

Pilot Aseptic St. Charles, IL

**Technician** *June* 2010 - 2012

Operated and maintained test-scale beverage processing equipment and utilities. Conducted trials on a wide variety of products.

- Tested effects of various thermal processes on clients' product formulations.
- Implemented necessary equipment modifications
- Maintained equipment and facility.
- Extensive on-the-fly trouble shooting of Alfa Laval VTIS & FLEX systems
- Created numerical heat-penetration model used by Pepsi Co. through present day

#### **Education**

Illinois Institute of Technology **Studied Applied Mathematics**  CHICAGO, IL 2004 - 2007

Focused on discreet methods

#### **Skills & Certifications**

Technical specialties: Networking. Python (NumPy, SciPy and Pandas), Ignition!. Familiar with SQL, ZPL, Git, LATEX, Modbus and Ethernet/IP. Advanced Excel skills.

Certifications: PCQI, HACCP, BPCS

## **Patents**

Sizer, C.E. and Sizer, C.E. IV. Method and Apparatus for sterilizing containers. US Patent 7,481,974 issued 27 January 2009.

Sizer, C.E. and Sizer, C.E. IV. Method and Apparatus for heating and dispensing sterile product. US Patent 7,595,470 issued 29 September 2009.

Sizer, C.E. and Sizer, C.E. U.S. Patent Application on Process for Making a Beverage Concentrate with a Low Concentration of Nucleation Sites.

# **Interests**

**Non-exhaustive and in alphabetical order:** cooking, computer security, hiking, kayaking, machine learning, rocket science, space exploration, sustainability